Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- James Joyce - Writings, 1904-1949; Series XV; 16
  - Anna Livia Plurabelle
    - Italian translation fragment, typescript, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1498)
    - Scenario adaptation by Stuart Gilbert, typescript carbon and setting pages, corrected (Box 64, Folder 1499)
  - "Comeallyou"
    - Holograph, 1937 Nov 11 (Box 64, Folder 1500)
    - Typescript, 1937 Nov
  - "Ecce Puer"
    - Typescript, 1932 Feb 15 (Box 64, Folder 1501)
    - French translation, Le Phare de Neuilly, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1502)
  - [Epiphanies?]
    - Fragment, typescript, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1503)
  - Exiles
    - Notes for Irish Jubilee [Maria Jolas?], n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1504)
  - Finnegans Wake
    - Corrections for second edition made with Paul Léon, typescript, photocopy, 1940 (Box 64, Folder 1505)
  - "Now I have Fed and Eaten up the Rose"
    - German text [by Gottfried Keller] and English translation, holograph (Box 64, Folder 1506)
  - "The Sister"
    - The Irish Homestead photocopy with notes, 1904 Aug 13 (Box 64, Folder 1507)
  - "Stephen's Green" ["Jakobsgrässlicher"] [translation of poem by James Stephens]
    - Typescript with holograph note, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1508)
  - Various
    - Royalty statements, 1941 (Box 64, Folder 1509)
- James Joyce - Photographs, 1880-1939; Series XVI; 9
  Series XVI is arranged alphabetically by subject of photograph.
  - Barnacle, Thomas, Mrs., ca. 1880? (Box 64, Folder 1510)
  - Four generations of Joyces, ca. 1937 (Box 64, Folder 1511)
  - Joyce, James
    - with Sylvia Beach and Adrienne Monnier at Shakespeare & Co., ca. 1920 (Box 64, Folder 1512)
    - with Family, Feldkirch, ca. 1932-34 (Box 64, Folder 1513)
    - in Field with unidentified man [glass negative], n.d.
    - with Prof. and Mme. S. Giedion, ca. 1930s (Box 64, Folder 1514)
    - with Michael Healy, ca. 1930
    - with Augustus John, ca. 1925-30
    - with Lucia Joyce, ca. 1932 (Box 64, Folder 1515)
    - Outing series with Lucia Joyce, Nora Joyce and Eugène Jolas, Feldkirch [with annotations by Lucia Joyce], 1932
    - Sideways angle shot, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1516)
    - Sitting poses and Grave marker, ca. 1930-32
    - with Philippe Soupault, ca. 1930
    - Standing pose, 1939 Sep (Box 64, Folder 1517)
    - in Zurich[?] on bridge, ca. 1939
  - Joyce, John
    - Gravesite, n.d.
  - Joyce, Lucia
    - Portraits, ca. 1932 (Box 64, Folder 1518)
  - Joyce, Nora
    - Sideways angle shot, ca. 1932
  - Joyce, Stephen [?]
    - with animals, ca. 1937
- James Joyce - Papers of Helen Joyce, 1920-1939; Series XVII; 12
  Series XVII is arranged alphabetically by type of material and name of correspondent.
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1920-39, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1519)
  - Correspondence
    - Beach, Sylvia, 1930 May 25 (Box 64, Folder 1520)
    - Boyle, Kay, 1939 Apr 13 (Box 64, Folder 1521)
    - Close, J. B., Mrs., 1939 Mar 13
    - Fernandez, Emile, 1939 Jan 9
    - Fleischman, David, ca. 1932-39 (Box 64, Folder 1522)
    - Gillet, Louis, 1939 Jan 9 (Box 64, Folder 1523)
    - Fontaine, J., 1937 Dec 17
    - Joyce, Stephen, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1524)
    - Kastor, Alfred, 1930-39
    - Kastor, Margot, 1939 (Box 64, Folder 1525)
    - Kastor, N-, n.d.
    - Kastor, Robert, 1939 (Box 64, Folder 1526)
    - Kastor, Sigmund, 1939 Apr 7
    - Lambert, C-, 1939 Jul 29 (Box 64, Folder 1527)
    - Monnier, Adrienne, 1939 Jun 18
    - Pound, Ezra (Box 64, Folder 1528)
    - Schubert, Dorothy, 1939 Apr 10
    - Turner, Rose, 1939 May (Box 64, Folder 1529)
    - Wright, Jean, n.d.
    - Unidentified - Hal, 1939 Mar 12
  - Medical Report, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1530)
- Oversize, 1924-1977; 4; (2 boxes)
  Oversize contains materials from Series II, IV, IX, X, and XI.
  - Eugène Jolas - Writings
    - Articles
      - "A Chronicle of Reviews," Chicago Tribune - Paris, 1926 Dec 26 (Box 67, Folder 1579)
      - "Rambles Through Literary Paris," Chicago Tribune - Paris, 1924
      - Vertigral [announcement for issue of transition containing sample works by Eugène Jolas, Georges Pelorson, Vincent Huidobro, Gabrielle Buffet, Leon-Paul Fargue, Hugo Ball and Hans Arp, 1932 Jul 15
    - Poetry
      - Other Poems
        - "Ahnungen," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1933 Jul 21 (Box 67, Folder 1580)
        - "Appel Orphique," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Apr
        - "Auf eine Zeitung in der Gosse," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Dec 2
        - "Aus den 'Amerikafahrer'," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1931 Dec 4
        - "Aus den 'Amerikafahrer'," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Feb
        - "In drei Sprachen," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1931 Aug 7
        - "Notules," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1931 Sep 11
        - "Pastorale," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1933 Oct 20 (Box 67, Folder 1581)
        - "Die Pilgerfahrt," et al., printed versions, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Jun-Jul
        - "Sion" and "Notules," printed version, Créer, 1925 Oct 16
    - Stories
      - "Document," printed version, Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Aug 26
  - Eugène Jolas - DENA
    - Propaganda posters, ca. 1944-45 (Box 67, Folder 1582)
    - Publications - Other
      - Munich after World War II, 1948 (Box 67, Folder 1583)
    - Public Press Information clippings, 1949
  - Maria Jolas - Translations
    - Hofmannsthal, Hugo von
      - A Few Poems
        - Cover illustration by Claire Illouz, [1977] (Box 68, Folder 1584)
    - Poster Book
      - French Text, 1959 Oct 6
      - English translation, galley proof, [1959]
  - Maria Jolas - Subject Files
    - James Joyce
      - Articles
        - Lapouge, Gilles "L'exil de Joyce" Le Quinzaine littéraire, 1969 Mar (Box 68, Folder 1585)
      - Colloquium - 1976, Buffalo
        - Exhibition catalog, 1976
      - Exhibitions - La Hune - 1948, Paris
        - Photographs, 1949 (Box 68, Folder 1586)
        - List of Photographs, [1949]
        - Portrait of Joyce by Wyndham Lewis [print], 1920
        - Poster, 1948 (Box 68, Folder 1587)
      - Symposium - 1975 - Paris
        - Poster, 1975
      - Theatrical productions - Finnegans Wake by Mary Manning
        - Poster, 1966 (Box 68, Folder 1588)
  - Maria Jolas - Personal Papers
    - École bilingue de Neuilly
      - Tax Documents, 1932-39 (Box 68, Folder 1589)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 1935-83; 0.25; (1 box)
  Box 69, restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult Access Services.
  - Box 17, folder 318 (Box 69, Folder 1590)
  - Box 17, folder 319 (Box 69, Folder 1591)
  - Box 64, folder 1503 (Box 69, Folder 1592)
- Restricted Papers